<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<content title="The Electric Looper Ensemble" lang="nl">
    <background caption="Background">
        <bg moment="morning" caption="06:00" />
        <bg moment="day" caption="14:00" />
        <bg moment="evening" caption="18:00" />
        <bg moment="night" caption="22:00" />
        <bg moment="sleep" caption="03:00" />
    </background>
    <header url="img/header_color.png">The Electric Looper Ensemble</header>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
        <p style="text-align:center;">
        <iframe width="100%" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NpEaa2P7qZI?controls=0" frameborder="0"></iframe>
        </p>
        ]]>
    </text>
    <title>What is "The Electric Looper Ensemble" ?</title>
    <text>
    <![CDATA[
        NL / Is a project initiated in 2019 by guitarist Emmanuel Istace. After years of interest in multiple genre and
        others' projects, this one is the convergence of his musical and software/electronic engineering skills.<br />
        The goal ? Perform "In C", alone, and provide a new experience of the piece to the audience every time.
        With a strong emphasis on "true" live performance, no automation or prerecorded material or synth/virtual
        instruments.<br />
        The ensemble is composed of a set of 8 independent loopers, the whole controlled by Emmanuel Istace, and his
        guitar as a sound brush.<br />
        For this performance, a lot of both musical and technical challenge had to be overcome, leading to months of
        preparation to perform this piece alone and provide a memorable experience for the audience.
        An emphasis had been made on the live performance, using a couple led matrix crates/speaker for each looper,
        as if they were performers on stage.
        Those crates/speaker can be organized on stage in row regarding their L/R panning or placed in a room where
        audience can navigate between each one, creating a different, yet interesting and immersive experience of the
        piece.
    ]]>
    </text>
    <title>What is "In C" ?</title>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
            "In C" is a piece composed by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terry_Riley">Terry Riley<a/>
            in 1964 for an undefined number of performers. It is a series of
            53 short melodic fragment and is usually considered as one the first minimalist piece written.
            During the performance, each musician have the control over continuing to play the current motif, moving to
            the next one or stop playing and wait to join back.
            That can be considered as kind of "composed improvisation", where each performers would rely on repetitive
            "licks".
            Due to the qualities of each fragment, music emerge from the performers choices, phasing play a major role
            in creating new interesting sound, melodies and textures.
            The piece has an average duration of 45 to 90 minutes, and is performed by "The Electric Looper Ensemble"
            usually in 30 to 45 minutes, each performance being unique.
            This performance consider each looper as an individual performer, so this could be considered an octet
            performance.
        ]]>
    </text>
    <image url="img/inc_score.gif">Score of In C by Terry Riley</image>
    <title>Why only use a single guitar ?</title>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
            It would be tempting to use different instruments, and it was envision at the beginning, to switch between
            an electric bass, fender stratocaster guitar, gibson es-125 guitar, nylon classical guitar and a mandoline.
            But it's even more challenging and satisfying for the performer and the audience to ear that variety of
            colors and texture coming from a single instrument. A great benefit is taken from the basic volume and
            tone controls on the guitar itself.
            <br />As Andres Segovia said: "the guitar is an orchestra", it's a major part of the interest a guitarist
            sustain toward his instrument over his musical journey. To discover, learn and control those different
            voices on the instrument, sometimes relying on "unorthodox" techniques. The guitar is like giving focus
            on a section of the orchestra, and that focus can be achieved by the variety of tone it can produce.
            <br />"The guitar is the only stringed instrument really polyphonic", said maestro Segovia too, meaning
            multiple notes can be played at the same time, while most of the other stringed instrument have to rely
            on arpeggios or limited polyphony for the average musician. But yet, the guitar is not like a piano, each
            string have her own character, her own soul and intentions, and the same pitch can be found on multiple
            places through different strings, yet, with singular remarkable differences between each. Those are then
            filtered by the performer technique who decide how those singular position will sound regarding their
            intrinsic characteristics.
            <br />Most think those qualities are lost outside of the truly acoustic nylon classical guitar, but same
            techniques and considerations leading to beautiful expressiveness apply to the electric guitar.
        ]]>
    </text>
    <title>What is Live Looping ?</title>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
                Live looping is a technique that consist or recording live a sound and playing it back, one or multiple
                times. <br />
                The main idea of live looping is to use no automation or pre-recorded materials during the performance,
                everything you ear, was played, recorded and mixed during the live performance by the artist.
                <br />
                For the need of this performance, <a href="http://www.circularlabs.com/">Mobius</a>
                was first used, hosted in <a href="https://www.reaper.fm/">Reaper</a>. But the encounter of
                <a href="https://www.facebook.com/TheLucidBrain/">Emmanuel Reveneau</a>,
                author of <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/NOundo/">NOundo</a>
                along way lead the artist to discover <a href="https://www.brainmodular.com/">Usine</a> and design a
                fully custom live environment.
        ]]>
    </text>
    <image url="img/usine.png">
        <![CDATA[
            Screenshot of <a href="https://www.brainmodular.com/">Usine HollyHock 4</a>, developed by
            <a href="https://www.brainmodular.com/about.html">Olivier Sens</a>, used as live performance software.
        ]]>
    </image>
    <image url="img/moonburst.png">
        Screenshot of Moonburst, developed by the artist. Moonburst is an
        arduino based solution for musician that aim to provide a generic midi open source interface that accept as
        many 'generic' controller as possible, keeping the cost factor really low, yet versatile and open. Some
        solutions already exists, but not as I envision mine, or at high costs and sometimes long learning curve.
    </image>
    <title>What are those crates ?</title>
    <text>
        <![CDATA[
            Each matrix is build around a design adapted by <a href="https://www.lghs.be/">Liège Hackerspace</a> from
            (TODO) project. It consist of a led within each bottle in crates, then controlled by an electronic
            device that allows to push information about what to display.
            For this case, each matrix/speaker are in fact independent.
            They all act as a receiver from their associated looper and act as autonomous unit.
            To communicate, they are all in network to share audio signal. Each crate allow to have a
            visual feedback of each loop through sound visualization
            algorithms.
        ]]>
    </text>
    <image url="img/matrix.jpg">
        <![CDATA[
            The <a href="https://www.lghs.be/">Liège Hackerspace</a> led matrix used in this project.
        ]]>
    </image>
    <band>Live footage coming soon...</band>
    <footer>
        <![CDATA[
            Project and website initiated in 2019 by <a href="https://emmanuelistace.be">Emmanuel Istace</a>.
        ]]>
    </footer>
    <modal title="Booking informations" link="Book Me!" closeCaption="Close" id="booking">
        <![CDATA[
            Thank you, your interest is really appreciated. <br /><br />
            You can send a mail to contact@emmanuelistace.be or
            <a href="mailto:contact@emmanuelistace.be">click here</a>
            to receive details about the performance.<br /><br />
            Talk to you soon.
        ]]>
    </modal>
</content>
